all right
[Music]
telomere length is considered a
biomarker of Aging shorter telomeres are
associated with decreased life
expectancy and increased rates of
age-related chronic diseases telomere
shortening has been shown to be
accelerated by oxidative stress and
inflammation so since plant foods
contain plenty of compounds with
antioxidants and anti-inflammatory
properties it's plausible that their
sustained consumption might help
counteract telomere attrition and indeed
if you pull all the best studies on the
impact of nutrition on telomere length
the consumption of vegetables fruits
beans and nuts has been associated with
positive effects on markers of
inflammation and oxidative stress in
parallel with longer telomeres by
contrast processed Meats alcoholic and
sugar sweetened Beverages and other
foods rich in saturated fats alcohol and
sugar are linked to an increase in
inflammation and oxidative stress in
parallel with shorter telomeres
in my last video on telomeres I featured
a randomized controlled trial showing a
whole food plant-based diet and
lifestyle program could actually
lengthen telomeres is it just because
they cut out the junk those eating the
most Ultra processed foods have been
found to have almost twice the odds of
having short telomeres maybe it's
because they cut out the processed meat
like bacon ham hot dogs lunch meat
sausage which had been associated with
not only like cancer and diabetes risk
but shorter telomeres as well meaning
accelerated cellular aging though just
having something like a steak was not
similarly associated with telomere
length
processed meat but not unprocessed red
meat is associated with shorter telomere
length this is perhaps due to the
particularly high concentrations of
glycotoxins the advanced glycation end
products as well as carcinogenic
nitrosamines in the processed meat that
may promote inflammation and oxidative
stress the only unprocessed meat
associated with shorter telomeres was
poultry for dairy it appears to be the
milk fat a national survey of thousands
of Americans found an association
between increased biological aging and
the consumption of high fat milk even
people just going up like one percent
milk fat from like one percent milk to
two percent milk low-fat milk to reduce
fat milk appeared to have more than four
years of additional biological aging we
think it's because of the saturated fat
given that saturated fats trigger an
inflammatory response not all plant
foods are good for you though french
fries and potato chip consumption
associated with shorter telomeres yes
fiber intake goes hand in hand with
longer telomeres as does higher
vegetable and fruit consumption but that
may be trumped by a deep fryer what
about the consumption of a high-fat
whole plant food like nuts we know
higher telomere building enzyme
activities associated with a higher
dietary antioxidant score and
botanically seeds are packed with
antioxidants and by seeds they mean any
food you can put in the ground and
sprout a whole plant like whole grains
beans chickpeas lentils nuts they're
naturally enriched in antioxidant
compounds that protect the seed DNA from
damage
four weeks of navy beans didn't seem to
affect telomere length though what about
nuts well based on how much your
telomeres shorten every year you can
estimate the rate of Aging in other
words two people can have the same
chronological they same calendar age but
suffer more or less effective cellular
aging so for example if you smoke a pack
a day for a decade your cells May age
about three years faster or if you drink
soda every day it's like almost two
years of additional aging so what about
nuts U.S adults of the same age would
experience almost two years less
biologic aging per ounce of nuts and
seeds consumed per day the amount I
recommend in my free daily dozen app
the estimated biologic aging Advantage
would be nearly one year for each 100
calories of nuts and seeds consumed
every day the researchers conclude that
clearly consumption of nothing seeds
accounts for Meaningful lower levels of
biologic Aging in U.S men and women but
that's just an association you don't
know if nuts can slow tell mere
shortening until you put it to the test
a randomized controlled trial
investigating whether the inclusion of
one or two ounces of walnuts a day for
two years would help maintain telomere
length which normally shortens with age
in the control group their telomeres
shortened as expected over those two
years whereas the Walnut group telomeres
maintain their length though the
difference didn't reach statistical
significance now that was measuring
average telomere length and it's
probably more telling to look at how
long the shortest telomeres are rather
than the average if you do that look at
the percentage of telomeres that are
particularly short the Walnut group does
Edge out over the control group it's
well as steps is the length of the
shortest telomeres the key biomarker on
the onset of senescence the researchers
conclude that the inclusion of walnuts
in the regular diet for two years tends
to delay leukocyte telomere shortening
in older individuals a study on
pistachio consumption two ounces a day
for four months reduce signs of DNA
damage but did not significantly slow
the rate of telomere shortening and this
study which randomized people to eat
more mixed nuts found a higher risk of
telomere shortening in the nut group for
which the researchers could offer no
explanation so it's not clear whether
nuts help with telomeres or not
most supplement intervention studies
observed null effects on telomere length
as well with the exception of green tea
36 elderly women were randomly divided
into two groups exercise alone or
exercise with green tea consumption for
five months and a significant boost in
telomere length in the green tea group
with no change from the placebo
green tea is essentially a green leafy
vegetable we dip in hot water how about
eating green leafy vegetables in fact
the healthiest kind cruciferous
vegetables like broccoli cabbage
collards and kale they pitted a Raw
versus cooked and found that cooked was
better than raw for reducing DNA damage
from a carcinogen but raw was more
anti-inflammatory consequently to fully
exploit the complexity of the health
promoting potential of Ethiopian kale
and by extension maybe other cruciferous
a mix of both raw and cooked vegetables
should be part of the diet okay but what
about for boosting the telomere
lengthening age reversal enzyme raw or
cooked which do you think a short-term
dietary intervention showed that cooked
but not raw boosted telomerase activity
in as short as five days eating one and
a quarter cups of this kale a day it was
thought that you'd need like four months
of a change to affect telomeres but this
study provides for the first time
evidence that telomerase activity can
respond in a matter of days to a food
intervention but not just any food but
the healthiest food out there
cruciferous dark green leafy vegetables
[Music]
foreign